

## **BIOGRAPHY AND ARTIST STATEMENT**

Johann Diedrick is an artist, engineer, and musician that makes installations, performances, and sculptures for encountering the world through our ears. He surfaces vibratory histories of past interactions inscribed in material and embedded in space, peeling back sonic layers to reveal hidden memories and untold stories. He shares his tools and techniques through listening tours, workshops, and open-source hardware/software. He is the founder of A Quiet Life, a sonic engineering and research studio that designs and builds audio-related software and hardware products for revealing new sonic possibilities off the grid. He is the Director of Engineering at Somewhere Good, a 2022 Future Imagination Collaboratory Fellow at the Tisch School of the Arts at NYU, a 2021 Mozilla Creative Media Award recipient, a 2020 Pioneer Works Technology resident, a member of NEW INC, and an adjunct professor at NYU's ITP program. His work has been featured in Wire Magazine, Musicworks Magazine, and presented internationally at MoMA PS1, Ars Electronica, Somerset House, and multiple NIME conferences, among others.

## **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Somewhere Good, New York City, New York, U.S.A.

Director of Engineering

January 2021 - Present

 Designed, developed, and deployed Somewhere Good's flagship iOS application, implenteing front-end designs in native iOS (Swift) and developing our backend systems in Python (Flask) to over 100 alpha testers

A Quiet Life, New York City, New York, U.S.A.

Founder and CEO

January 2020 - Present

- Designed, developed, and deployed audio-based web applications, native mobile applications, data science, and machine learning projects for clients ranging from artists, scientists, and educators
  - http://aquiet.life/
- Designed, developed, and deployed Dark Matters, an interactive web experience that puts visitors into the seat of a machine learning researcher encountering the absense of Black speech in datasets used to train voice interface systems like Alexa, Google Home, and Siri
  - https://darkmatters.ml/
- Designed, developed and built the Harvester, a hand-held, portable live sampler and synthizer
  that lets you make music with everyday sounds. With the instrument, you are able to capture
  sounds around you (your voice, another musical instrument, environmental noises etc.). The
  instrument provides an interface that lets you play back the sampled sound based around a
  musical, pentatonic scale. This allows for a wildly expressive sonic palette that can be used for
  musical performance and sound art installations
  - http://aquiet.life/objects/harvester
- Built an environmental sound classifier web application using deep learning techniques with fast.ai (PyTorch, Pandas, NumPy) to classify sound recordings across 50 different categories
  - https://whisp.onrender.com/
  - http://aquiet.life/software/whisp
- Lead the development of an interactive music mobile application (iOS/C++) called Format No. 1 and Format No. 2 for Danish artists Louise Foo and Martha Skou, which is in the App Store and has been shown internationally in galleries and art events
  - http://aquiet.life/software/formatno1
  - http://aquiet.life/software/formatno2





## The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York City, New York, U.S.A.

Senior Software Developer

April 2015 - December 2019

- Lead the development of our backend system (developed in Python) that powered the Met Museum's mobile app, delivering fresh content with over 1,660 app sessions per day
- Lead the development and architecture of our first internal API (developed in Go), which
  was based on microservice practices and serves our Collection object pages, getting over
  700,000 average requests per day
- Lead the development of our Open Access Public API (developed in Go), which provides object data for over 500,000 objects in the Met's collection and is accessed over 150,000 times daily by users around the world
- Lead the development of our Open Access CSV initiative (developed in Go), which also provides object data for over 500,000 objects in the Met's collection, has over 400 stars on Github and is used by scholars and data scientists around the world
- Developed front end features for our newly redesigned object page (developed in C#, HTML5, CSS3 and Javascript), including our language localization feature and our A/B analytics testing framework, which has 25,982,621 unique page views and 6,280,385 unique users past in the past 12 months

**Qosmo**, Tokyo, Japan Software Developer June 2013 – March 2014

 Developed and installed audiovisual installations, mobile applications (iOS/Android) and experimental web applications

# **EDUCATION**

### New York University, Tisch School of the Arts

New York City, New York, U.S.A. M.P.S. in the Interactive Telecommunications Program May 2013 Honors: Fox Television-Benjamin L. Hooks Fellowship

## University of Pennsylvania, College of Arts and Sciences

Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, U.S.A. Bachelors of Arts in Sociology of Culture May 2009

### TECHNICAL EXPERTISE

- Object-oriented programming: C++ (OpenFrameworks), Objective-C, Swift (iOS), Java (Android, Processing)
- Backend development: Go (Gin, Echo), Python (Flask), Ruby (Ruby on Rails)
- Front-end development: HTML5, CSS3, Javascript
- Machine Learning / Deep Learning / AI: fast.ai, PyTorch, Pandas, Matplotlib, Librosa
- Dataflow programming: Max/MSP + Jitter, PureData
- Physical computing: Arduino, Raspberry Pi, DMX lighting, Microsoft Kinect
- Computer-aided design: Rhino, Vectorworks, Adobe Creative Suite, Final Cut Pro
- Digital fabrication: Laser cutter, CNC machine and 3D printer
- Basic analog circuitry: Audio circuits, Eagle, Othermill



## **AWARDS AND GRANTS**

### 2022

Future Imaginary Collaboratory Fellowship, Tisch School of the Arts, NYU

### 2021

Mozilla Creative Media Awards Recipient, Mozilla

Media Art Assistant Fund Grant Recipient, Wave Farm

Future Imaginary Collaboratory Fellowship, Tisch School of the Arts, NYU

### 2020

2020 Brooklyn Arts Fund Grant Recipient, Brooklyn Arts Council

#### 2019

Collaborator-In-Residence at MANCC, Florida State University, for Jonathan González

## 2016

Asian Cultural Council 2016 Grant Fellowship Recipient

## RESIDENCIES, EXHIBITIONS AND PERFORMANCES

#### 2021

- Dark Matters, (Solo Exhibition), Squeaky Wheel, Buffalo, New York
- Dark Matters, (Group Exhibition), Science Gallery Dublin, Dublin, Ireland
- Cerulean Waters, (Group Exhibition), Cuchifritos Gallery, New York, New York
- A Quiet Life (Talk), Maryland Institute College of Art (MICA), Baltimore, Maryland
- The Great Indoors (Workshop), Interaccess, Toronto, Canada

## 2020

- Artist-in-Residence (Technology), Pioneer Works, Brooklyn, New York
- Artist-in-Residence, Squeaky Wheel, Buffalo, New York
- Artist-in-Residence, Shell House, Roxbury, New York
- · Cerulean Waters (Performance), Un/Sounding the Relational City, NYU, New York, New York
- Flights of Fancy (Talk), Localhost, Recurse Center, Brooklyn, New York





- A Quiet Life (Talk), Experiential Music Hackathon, Brooklyn, New York
- Flights of Fancy (Talk), Interaccess, Toronto, Canada
- The Sudden Quiet (Soundscape), Radiophrenia, Centre for Contemporary Arts, Glasgow,
   Scotland

### <u>2019</u>

- Lucifer Landing I by Jonathan González (Sound Design), MoMA PS1, Queens, New York
- Lucifer Landing II by Jonathan González (Sound Design), Abrons Art Center, New York, New York
- Black Mayo (Soundscape), Radiophrenia, Centre for Contemporary Arts, Glasgow, Scotland
- Cerulean Waters (Soundscape), HOLO, Brooklyn, New York
- Cerulean Waters (Sound installation), Smiling Hogshead Ranch, Queens, New York
- Orchids (Performance), Recess, Brooklyn, New York

## 2018

- Take Your Time With Me (Performance), Sunday Service, Knockdown Center, Queens, New York
- Good Vibrations (Installation), Wilder LIC, Flux Factory, Queens, New York
- Good Vibrations Acoustic Cartography Tour (Workshop), Wilder LIC, Flux Factory, Queens,
   New York
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Wilder LIC, Flux Factory, Queens, New York
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), Terminal Dogma, Brooklyn,
   New York
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), HOLO, Brooklyn, New York
- Reflect/Refract (Installation), Remain Alert and Have a Safe Day, Local Project, Queens,
   New York
- Good Vibrations Acoustic Cartography Tour (Workshop), Remain Alert and Have a Safe Day,
   Local Project, Queens, New York
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), Remain Alert and Have a Safe
   Day, Local Project, Queens, New York
- Harvester (Workshop), Somerset House Studios, Music Hackspace, London, UK
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Somerset House Studios, Music Hackspace, London, UK
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), DIY Space for London, London, UK



- Acoustic Catrography Sound Walk, L28 Railway Area, Brussels, Belgium
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Common Ground, Berlin, Germany
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), Common Ground, Berlin, Germany
- · Sound Monsters (Workshop), Press Play, Pioneer Works, Brooklyn, New York
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), Sonic Transmission Archive,
   Newberg, New York
- When The Storm Has Passed, Spring Will Come (Performance), An Envelope in Cloud Sound Night, New York, New York

### 2017

- Sirens (Installation) Long Winter, Toronto, Canada
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Invisible Places, Ponta Delgada, Azores, Portugal
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Invisible Places, Ponta Delgada, Azores, Portugal
- Quiet Music, Weak Sounds (Residency), Social Kitchen, Kyoto, Japan
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Social Kitchen, Kyoto, Japan
- Field Recording (Workshop), Social Kitchen, Kyoto, Japan
- Aeolian Harp (Workshop), Social Kitchen, Kyoto, Japan
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Social Kitchen, Kyoto, Japan
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Meisei University, Tokyo, Japan
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), New York University,
   Shanghai, China
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), Shanghai, China
- Sirens (Installation) Reuptake, Little Berlin, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, U.S.A.
- It Is Impossible To Know About Earth So We Must Hear Her Voice In Our Own Way (Installation),
- Met Staff Art Show, Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, New York, U.S.A.
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Detective Squad, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Outdoor Sound Performance (Performance), New York, New York, U.S.A.
- Colorful Waves (Workshop), Parsons School of Design at the New School, New York, New York, U.S.A.





Colorful Waves (Workshop), Detective Squad, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.

### 2016

- Artist-In-Residence, Public Science, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Soundscape Symposium, Yale University, New Haven,
   Connecticut
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Computer Music Multidisciplinary Research Symposium,
   São Paulo, Brazil
- My Favorite Sound is You (Residency), The Galallery, San Francisco, California, U.S.A.
- Colorful Waves (Workshop), The Galallery, San Francisco, California, U.S.A.
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), The Galallery, San Francisco, California, U.S.A.
- A Quiet Life (Artist Talk), The Galallery, San Francisco, California, U.S.A.
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Toronto International Electroacoustic Symposium, Toronto, Canada
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Musichackspace, London, England
- Sounds Like You (Artist Talk), Musichackspace, London, England

## 2015

- Transmissions (Performance), Pioneer Works, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Transients (Performance), Yami Ichi, Queens, New York, U.S.A.
- My Favorite Sound is You (Residency), Being Generation Gallery, Toronto, Canada
- The Naked Ear: Tools and Techniques in Sound Art (Workshop), Reverse Space, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Brooklyn Acoustic Ecology Festival, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.

## <u>2014</u>

- Artist-In-Residence, Public Science, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Strings (Installation), Telefonica, Santiago, Chile, U.S.A.
- Strings (Installation), Google Adwords Performance Forum, Half Moon Bay, California, U.S.A.
- · Miku Miku Ni Shite Ageru (Video Projection), Powerball, The Power Plant, Toronto, Canada
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Invisible Places Sounding Cities, Viseu, Portugal



- Miku Miku Ni Shite Ageru (Video Projection), +81 Gallery, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- Transmissions (Performance), Ace Hotel, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Songs For Backs (Performance), Death By Audio, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- A Haunting (Installation), Death By Audio, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.

### <u>2013</u>

- Strings (Installation) Dumbo Arts Festival, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- A Haunting (Performance), 13th International NIME Conference, Daejeon and Seoul, Korea
- Sounds Like You (Documentation), ITP Spring Show 2013, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Good Vibrations (Listening Tour), Megapolis NYC, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Wormhole Follies (Performance), Big Screens, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Strings (Installation), Ventana 244, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.

### 2012

- A Haunting (Installation), ITP Winter Show 2012, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- A Haunting (Performance, ITP NIME Winter Performance, Glasslands Gallery, Brooklyn, New York, U.S.A.
- A Haunting (Installation), Viewers Like You, Judson Memorial Church, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Grand Dream (Documentation), New Biologies, 92Y Tribeca, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Cicadas (Performance), Yamaguchi Center for Arts and Media, Yamaguchi, Japan
- Strings (Installation), NIME 2012 Conference, Ann Arbor, Michigan, U.S.A.
- Grand Dream (Documentation and Demonstration), ITP Spring Show, New York City, New York, U.S.A.
- Grand Dream (Performance and Installation), Rose Schlossberg's Apartment, New York City, New York, U.S.A.

## 2011

• Strings (Installation), ITP Winter Show, New York City, New York, U.S.A.





### **PRESS**

- On Love & Data: To Be Heard Without Limitation by Stephanie Dinkins (November 2021)
   https://pioneerworks.org/broadcast/on-love-and-data-stephanie-dinkins
- Witches, Angels, and Thieves: I'm Thinking of Sampling Things by Max Levin (Summer 2021) https://www.owenchristoph.com/shop/stopgap003
- Sounding The Unknown by Robert Barry, Wire Magazine (April 2017)
   https://www.thewire.co.uk/issues/398 (English)
   (PDF of the article is available here: <a href="http://www.johanndiedrick.com/static/docs/">http://www.johanndiedrick.com/static/docs/</a>

   Johann Diedrick-Sounding The Unknown-The Wire-April 2017.pdf)
- Artspiration, RTHK (July 2018)
   http://www.rthk.hk/tv/dtt31/programme/adcweekly\_artspiration/episode/502215
   (Chinese)
- Good Vibrations, City Plants (November 2017)
   https://cityplants.us/interviews/good-vibrations-2/ (English)
- ヨハン・ディードリッヒ × 柳沢英輔 インタビュー (April 2017) 2017)
   http://www.kansaiartbeat.com/kablog/entries.ja/2017/05/quiet-music-weak-sounds.
   html (Japanese)
- 京都で「小さな音」に耳を傾ける。サウンドアーティストと音文化研究者によるワークショップ https://bijutsutecho.com/news/2891/ (Japanese)
- 静かな音楽、小さな音」に耳を傾けるワークショップ/イベント「Quiet Music, Weak Sounds」京都で 開催 (March 2017)

http://www.cbc-net.com/event/2017/04/quiet-music/ (Japanese)

Quiet Music, Weak Sounds -静かな音楽、小さな音 (April 2017)
 http://hanareproject.net/event/2017/04/quiet-music-weak-sounds---.php (Japanese and English)



- Good Vibrations by Dennis Kastrup, Radio Eins (January 2017)
   https://www.radioeins.de/programm/sendungen/modo1316/strom-und-drang/good-vibrations.html (German)
- APA / JØ. Der Stromausfall / Cloudbursting by Kristel Jax, Musicworks Magazine (Spring 2016)

https://www.musicworks.ca/reviews/recordings/apa-j%C3%B8-der-stromausfall-cloudbursting (English)

- インターネットヤミ市 in NY!フォトレポート! by tadahi, CBCNET, (November 2015)
   http://www.cbc-net.com/log/?p=8830 (Japanese)
   http://aquiet.life/transients/yamiichi\_cbc (English)
- What I Learned About Creativity by Watching Creatives by Clay Shirky, PSFK (May 2012)
   http://www.psfk.com/2012/05/clay-shirky-psfk-conference-talk.html (English)